Ultimately, the identity question is how do I ensure that
when an agent does make a mistake, it doesn't do something catastrophic
I didn't intend.
This thing is built on like a probabilistic distribution.
The feature is that it can reason and it can guess over large amounts of data.
Right.
And that it is non-deterministic.
That's the feature.
The bug from a security perspective is that it's non-deterministic
and that is still the feature.
So the feature and the bug are the same.
And the final question is how do I know that an agent is performing
actions aligned with the intent of whoever set that agent to do something.
The AI Native Dev is a podcast for developers and engineering
leads at the cutting edge of AI and agentic coding.
Join your hosts, Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple.
Every week as we chat with the most exciting voices in
AI and tackle the biggest questions facing developers today.
This is the AI Native Dev.
We just
wrapped up two amazing days at AI Native DevCon in London.
But the great thing is that
we get to do it all over again in New York City this November.
You're absolutely right.
We're going to be back in the city that never sleeps on November 3rd and
4th for more amazing sessions, really engaging hands-on workshops and much more.
Yeah, all that great networking, partying, eating and
drinking that you've come to expect from AI Native DevCon.
We think we have one of the best hallway tracks in the business,
and it's the perfect complement to our incredible speakers and presenters.
We'll both be in person and virtual,
with live streamed access to all mainstage keynotes and talks.
Sign up right now for our Super Blind Bird ticket for just $100.
Only available for a limited time.
We're really excited to be headed back to the Big Apple, and we hope
to see you all there.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome back to the AI Native Dev.
We are in kind of an ad hoc office over here.
You know, actually sort of Ian's hometown, or like.
Current home.
Base at the moment here in San Francisco as part of the AI Engineer event
and really kind of enjoying a lot of AI conversations on it.
And today we're going to dive in to identity.
Identity.
If you've been sort of exploring the security realm of agents,
identity really has been the top topic of it.
Everybody appreciates that.
It is a foundational aspect of how do you get these agents
to actually be secure and kind of work and give them some autonomy.
And so to kind of demystify this whole domain and understand how to tackle that,
we've got Ian Livingstone, who is the co-founder of Keycard. Yep.
That is a sort of a really exciting company in the identity space.
But also really, Ian is really sharp
and deep around explaining things as a whole and specifically identity.
Known him from Snyk days, and his sort of past companies
that he's founded on it.
So we'll we'll learn about identity, learn about what you can do.
And we will hear a little bit about Keycard.
Super excited as well. Yeah.
For coming on. Thanks for having me.
I'm super excited to talk about identity and agents and security
and this whole bundle of things together today and really help
people understand sort of one is like, what's the problem?
Why this is a hot topic.
Like, why is it, like, identity is like kind of boring or a snoozefest?
It's been for years, you know.
But why is this hot again?
And why are people thinking about it and how that actually changes the way
that we actually think, by the way we build systems
and also how autonomous these systems can become. Yeah. Yeah.
Well, let's not back over here.
So let's, let's get started.
Just tell us a little bit about what are the, the problems or sort of the,
you know, give us a bit of a structure for thinking about identity and agents.
Absolutely.
So I think I think the first step we have to think about is like,
why is identity even a thing we talk about?
Like if we were to step back and like identity
has been a part of computing for as long as it's existed, right.
The minute you had a mainframe. And then I want to have multiple users.
Now you have a new problem, which is like, what files or programs on
the system are Guy's programs and files and what files and systems are Ian's,
and how does Guy get access to all of Ian's stuff, or does he have access?
Like, it's been like every wave of computing introduces this question of,
well, who can do what, when and where. And who.
Can access. Exactly. Like, in high school,
hacking, getting into all sorts of information systems
that I was not supposed to be in? Not exactly.
And, you know, in the rise of the internet
brought about, like, when we initially, it was like TLS brought about commerce.
And so every wave of computing comes with that net new security challenges
we have to solve because the like the interaction patterns change
when we introduce new paradigms, look the rise of the cloud and then etc.,
you know, with IAM and identity for cloud vendors and GCP and secret sprawl.
We've always had these problems.
And so agents like many things, as we introduce new functionality
and capability, like platform shift, we have to reassess our security model.
And the core crux of the identity problem when it comes to agents is
this thing is built on like a probabilistic distribution.
It's a statistical training, right?
It's beautiful.
The feature is that it can reason and it can guess over large amounts of data.
Right.
And that it is non-deterministic.
That's the feature.
The bug from a security perspective is that it's non-deterministic
and that is still the feature.
So the feature and the bug are the same.
And the final question is how do I
know that an agent is performing
actions aligned with the intent of whoever set that agent to do something, right,
which is like the foremost question of
this generation, and there's many different parts of that.
Right? You've got supply chain security as a part of it.
Data security is a part of it.
But identity is very foundational.
And thinking through how do I have a secure agent?
It's also foundational to think of through how do I enable an agent
to be autonomous.
Right.
And the more autonomous an agent becomes, or the more autonomous you want
agent to be, the security equation becomes much more difficult to solve.
And the systems that used to work
in the last, last era start to stop working as much in the new era.
Right.
And that's I think that's a fundamental sort of thing to understand.
And then ultimately, the identity question is how do I ensure
that when an agent does make a mistake, it doesn't do something catastrophic?
I didn't intend. Right.
And so today, if you have paid attention or have read, there's
lots of different problems associated with identity that people talk about.
One of them would be
you have supply chain attacks
that result in database passwords and keys being leaked, like the most recent LLM
and attacks where the actual attack vector was, how do I take long
lived API keys off of disk and use those to exfiltrate data?
But there's other problems of how do I,
you know, when I use an agent, if I ask an agent to do something?
This was very common six months ago.
Ask the agent to optimize a database.
A potential path to optimizing a database would actually.
Be, delete the data. Exactly, right.
And so that does make it snappy. But that.
Would be deeply unaligned with what the actual user wants that agent to do.
And so that's fundamentally a question of authorization and access.
And the difference between what we've had and what with agents is
I actually want to give agents access to different things depending upon the job
I've assigned them to do or the task of something to do.
And that's a very different model we've had previously. Yeah, yeah.
So I think there's there's basically a few aspects that you,
that you have on over there.
So one aspect of it is, is is the non-determinism.
Right.
The safety is like, how likely is the agent to sort of choose to do a thing
that is not a thing that would have otherwise kind of been
consented or allowed on it.
So I guess there's sort of a broader safety element.
And some of that comes down to, you know, harnesses and context
and all that of, of, of, of trying to sort of steer
the agents to understand where the lines are
and I guess that's that's not really identity.
Those are like agent workflows.
But then next to that,
I think we have sort of two aspects of identity that you touch on there.
One is, you know, who is the agent, you know,
what is the sort of entity, right, that I'm assigning it.
And the second is the the permissions.
You know, I guess we talk about authentication and authorization and identity.
So I guess how do you am I kind of dividing that correctly over here?
And maybe if we put safety as a massively interesting topic on its own,
but do you think they're intertwined or, and, or do you just need to worry
about all of them?
I think, I think if, when a business, when you step back and ask, is it safe?
Or another way to think is, do I trust an agent to be able to perform this action?
Yeah.
You know, identity and access, delegation, all these things
are vital components of that, as they are in every other era of computing.
And, you know, to a certain extent
when it comes to identity and access, there
you you'll have deterministic controls around what agents can do.
And you'll have non-deterministic controls.
And, like, a good example is
safety work often is about how do I bias a model into that
it is, it is not affected, or, you know, does what I want.
So it's not going to do the bad thing or has less probable to do the bad thing.
But for from a security equation you want to say,
well, there's a set of things that I just want to never happen.
I want to guard, like, I don't want a guardrail, I want
I want a hard boundary around what it can do.
And it's part of this is also the reason why
things like sandbox is very popular right now.
It's like, I can never 100%
know the model may not do this.
So, but I need, in order for me
to put this into production, for this type of workload or perform
this type of task,
I need to ensure that it has a hard boundary so it can never happen.
So I can say as a business, yes.
You know, the worst case scenarios that I worry about
have actually been removed from the equation.
And then the rest of the things that are left, it's like kind of okay,
if that happens, like it's not great if it does something weird,
but it's not going to
destroy the business or result in lost customer data or on and on and on it goes.
So there's one aspect of defining the sandbox,
and you're saying, I know that these things won't happen.
Exactly.
You know, if I want the agent to do useful things,
it might not delete all of my inbox, but I'm still getting it as an email.
Exactly.
It can still do unsafe things over there, but if it doesn't have access to my
records, it's not going to send.
Me outside. Okay.
So so there's we're we're talking now
a little bit more about that sort of boundary zone. Exactly.
So what are the types of agent identity conversation that we have.
Yeah I think I think there's one is sort of where we're coming from.
Right.
And if you look at sort of the identity systems of last generation,
like the way I would give
a piece of software access to something is I would give an API key, it would maybe
be a service account, or represent a service account, potentially
it would maybe represent a user because it was a user's
API key or personal access token.
It was like we built a world based on shared secrets
and the issue with shared secrets
is they're often bound strictly to a specific identity, and they're bound
strictly to a set of permissions associated with that long lived secret.
And the more important thing is, if that secret were leaked, anyone
who got access to that shared password also could do that thing.
And now the the fundamental challenge is okay
knowing that that's where we came from.
How do we move to a world where I want.
I'm Guy.
I really want this agent to operate over a very long period of time
on my behalf,
because it's going to have access to my Gmail or have access to my Google Drive.
But if at any point it needs to perform a write action.
So, send an email on my behalf, I should probably get to approve it, right.
And like fundamentally,
the process of going through is as we go up the autonomy curve.
So we go from, I'd love to use a self-driving car
analogy as we go from level zero, which is deterministic software,
GPT to Copilots, which is like level one to something
that's like slightly, or tab complete from Cursor, to sort of like
Cursor agents and Claude Code agents, which are like level two.
Is a human still involved?
How do we actually go from a world where, like as we go up that autonomy ladder,
I, I'm retaining security over what that thing is doing.
And if, you know, currently if you were to use Cursor or Claude
when it goes into a tool call, oftentimes they're saying, hey Guy.
Do you want to do that? Do you always want to do that?
No, you don't want to do it on everything.
And so the question is you can't have autonomy
when the human has to constantly be in the loop,
which is where these access systems come in, which is saying as I go
up the autonomy ladder.
So as we want to get to this sort of self-driving car analogy,
there's a trust and safety equation that is with that,
which is how do I keep this thing driving on the road
instead of driving off the road, off the cliff or whatever it may be?
And that's at the crux of it, what we're actually all talking about, right?
Yeah.
So I feel like the word identity is like can be a little bit confusing here
because there's like one question is
I've got this agent, it's running on my behalf.
Can I know that it is the agent.
So, like, I feel when I hear identity, I think primarily who is it that is acting
and that might be, you know, is it me talking or is it my agent talking?
So can the system separate the two of us?
It might be.
Is my agent talking
to another agent to perform actions on behalf of agents all the way down.
Right.
They they cascade down.
So that's one aspect.
But a lot of the attention you draw is actually to, to the kind of
to its decisions. Right.
Like, you know, as it comes along, it might be it's around
the communication of when I delegate a task. Yes.
What is not just the the knowledge that it is my agent,
but rather what is its scoped permissions right now within this one,
like you can compose the email, but you are not allowed to send the email.
Exactly.
So is that, I guess people, like, again, the word identity is used for the market
on it.
How do you separate this sort of authentication from authorization?
Yeah.
So this is interesting because if you look at in the identity
world, the cloud. When we were getting to the cloud, it was really about, can I verify
that Guy is in fact Guy Podjarny.
When Guy goes to Google Drive, like, that
the basis of cloud was really focused on that.
And authorization didn't really fall into the problem space.
And that's because at the time,
we didn't
really have to solve authorization, and we didn't have to solve authorization,
because if I could identify that it's Guy and I trust Guy,
then I can give Guy really broad based access, because implicitly
we've we've done the background check.
We called all the references.
He, you know, isn't isn't a sociopath, right.
Like it turns out.
Well yeah. You did hide it. Well.
It turns out that Guy really cares about how people think about him.
And he wants to do a good job.
And it turns out that if he got fired from the job, that'd be devastating.
So the implicitly, we can
we can trust that Guy is going to operate with high intent and not be malicious.
Right?
The part is because it's the same Guy that will sort of come in to the next task.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Well, the agents are basically a brand new creature.
Exactly. A brand new creature every time with different context.
And they don't have, they have no sense of is this good or wrong?
Like they're not malicious. Yeah, right.
They just don't know. And there isn't a way for them to say it.
Do I know or do I not know? Right.
That's authoritative in a way that a human can be.
And so from that perspective, agents
really change that equation where it used to be that, okay.
If I just know it's a human
and I trust that human, once it's all configured, it kind of works.
Now it's based on the thing that I've assigned them and the data
that they have about that thing.
I'm going to give them different levels of access based on
what's in that context window, and so much about this next generation.
It is about authorization, which is, what things can this do?
But it's also about what things has this agent seen or done.
So I know that it is in a well bounded box
on whether it should have access to that.
And if I can't call that judge, if I can't make a decision, like a system
can't make the decision, the system can also be like,
you know what, actually,
maybe I need to go talk to Guy and be like,
hey Guy, can you review this thing that the agent wants to do before it goes
and does it?
And so much of if if what we're trying to do is to basically
turn software into the Waymo experience, so much of it is like,
how do we, as the models improve, how do we, over time,
give them more autonomy but with the same substrate system?
Because there's going to be certain tasks that you assign an agent
you're going to say, you know what, it's totally summarization.
Where I'm pulling in a bunch of context, I'm summarizing a document for you.
You should have it's okay, read access to everything.
That's totally fine.
But the minute you want to go and do a high,
maybe a transaction that costs over $500, definitely.
That's maybe that's when a human has to say, you know what?
I don't trust agents to make decisions on my behalf.
Over $500. Or an organization
may say I don't trust agents to have access to customer data at all.
Like there are different trust equations, and every person and organization,
depending upon the context of what
the agent is, who's using it, and what things it's asking
will have a different trust equation about what they think is okay for them.
Yeah, yeah.
Interesting.
So really what you want is you want the the identity.
I really like this identity plus authorization bundle.
Exactly. Task based.
Yes. I'm performing a task.
This task should have a set of permissions. Exactly.
So I think within that world it feels there are two,
two, simplifying a little bit, two ways in which sort of agents work.
Right.
One is an agent as in an agent workflow.
And so I'm running it.
And so, you know I can choose
sometimes it's doing broad things, sometimes it's doing narrow things.
But I think within that world it feels quite kind of manageable to say
I'm giving it a delegation.
We'll come back a little bit to how do I define which permissions.
Yeah, that's a different
problem, that is sort of a hard problem, but, but at least I know
like this bundle, this sort of this sort of this process here that is executing.
It's, it's
kind of executing the same thing or like this assigned action again.
Again.
And then I've got, like, my kind of Claude Code or Codex or Gemini
running locally. Yes.
And I don't know, like, probably like my
in my IDE, or like Claude that I'm running on my stuff,
I don't, it doesn't do one thing. Like, I do one thing and then I come back.
This is like, yeah, I've got this other one.
And oftentimes just sort of run in like one long session
that I walk around and, you know, if I just approve of things like,
okay, I just performed an action and said,
can I delete this file and delete this file?
And this was like, final, and delete all, like, yes, always approve.
And then I come along and do something else
and you know, that goes away.
Is that a lost cause.
Like, is that, that it's like, hey Guy, just stop using the agent like that,
like use it in a more methodical fashion and to do that, or
is there a better model that have to.
There's definitely a better model,
like what we want to get to as a world where agents you can assign agent
a task, a task, maybe something, hey, do, like, survey the internet and every day
come back to me. Or survey all of my assets,
all of my inbox, and come back to me and tell me what happened, right?
And that's like, that's a long live process where you definitely don't
want every morning to wake up and have to click a consent screen, right.
You actually just like I've assigned you, I've given I've delegated authority
to you to perform things
on my behalf. And in order for me to delegate to this agent and that agent.
Actually, this is where identity comes in.
We have to be able to identify the agent, right?
So it's like, I've given Foobar agent
for the context, for this task, this authority.
And when I sent it a different task, I wanted to give it different authority.
But that's the first basis.
It's like this is why we talk about identity is okay.
Well, in order to give something
your authority to do something on your behalf,
you both have to be able to have to be able to identify that thing.
And then the thing that the downstream systems that are saying,
hey, is this random request that's coming into my system,
does it have the permissions?
Like, has it been given the authority to do the thing it's asking to do?
Well, I have to both know.
Well, oh, Guy did in fact give Foobar access to do this thing,
but I have to actually be able to identify both Foobar and Guy.
And certainly those systems want to treat an access request
or request based from Guy differently than they do from Foobar.
Because, when you think, I love to give the example of, like, credit card
chargebacks here, because if you ask your agent to perform
a transaction on your behalf and then you say, hold up a second,
I didn't give it access to do that. Yeah.
How does the intermediary be like?
Well, actually, no, we have a record, in fact, that you did tell Foobar
to go and do this thing and that you said it could spend up to $500
and it did do that thing.
So we're actually not going to process
that chargeback, because you did do it with today's identity systems.
What we built in the last generation, you can't differentiate between
what did Guy give Foobar that access for, this
specific task or a different task, or where's Foobar in the mix?
None of that.
None of that existed
because we actually didn't have to build that for last generation security posture.
And now we we do. Yeah.
So I guess I'm going back a little bit and we'll get a little bit to solutions.
I'm hearing three levels here.
One is separate me from my agent.
So use identities that are specific for.
Two, is have a set of authorizations that is,
that is aligned to the task that you've just given the agent.
And I guess three, which relates a little bit to the two, is
if you're within like the second one is easy when you've defined the task
upfront and it's not a long lived agent, but when it's a long lived agent.
Am I right in understanding that you're saying there's
another kind of bucket of, like, ephemeral entity, the sort of entity
that comes along, which is what is the current task being done?
Exactly?
That is like kind of like gathered out of the moment in time,
the last few messages,
whatever it is, you know, the last message that the user has provided where it is.
Yeah.
And I guess that type of activity,
you know, it really isn't a place in which the human will engage.
So that probably needs to itself be more kind of inferred or decided.
Is that right?
So that's right.
The first one and the second one are a scale problem
of a thing that we had before. We had a system.
We gave the system a task.
We had to give it a, we had to give. It.
A permission set.
But this third one, that's a new creature. Totally.
And if you were to go and read current literature, you will find that
what you and I are talking about,
like I think task was very understandable
for us to think about, is like, hell yeah, I assigned this thing a job or a task
to go do, and it went and did it on behalf.
And maybe that task
is repeated every 30 days, or it takes a long time to do that task.
In literature, it's called
a mission. It's like, often in standards that are starting to emerge.
This concept of a mission and a mission is over time, as users
or other people give assigned work for these things to do,
you're going to think about here are the missions
or the quests I've assigned to this thing, and I, as a user,
will update what that mission is as we learn things.
And really what that mission is, is about.
Describing the user's intent as a concrete thing.
It's like,
I intend for this agent to be able to, you know, complete this type of task.
And that allows another system like an authorization system
to understand, hey, this user or this company, right?
Somebody has assigned a mission to this agent.
That mission is something I can measure their access
requests against and say, is this aligned with human intent?
So that gives us a way to think about how the concept
of an agent's identity and the tasks they're working on travels across systems.
Right.
Which is the issue that doesn't exist at all today. Is, if you go to Uber
and you ask your agent to book on your behalf, Uber
has actually no way to know whether you, what the action
that the agent is performing was aligned with what your initial request was at.
All, right.
And so part of this is like, we have this new concept, as in delegation, is this
what is it that this thing has been assigned to do,
so that I can then judge whether the thing it's asking to
do is aligned with a thing it was assigned to do.
Right?
So this is like a so we have human identities.
We have non-human identities.
And is there now a mission identity there? There is.
And typically this is there's there's in
you can think of these concepts inside identity.
There's this concept of session for a long time. Right.
It's like, I log into a website, that creates a session, often from 1990 to 2000.
Web. It's a cookie in your browser, and that represents some session.
And that session helps identify who you are.
And now it's not just, a session isn't just who you are.
It's who are you acting on behalf of.
And it is also for what purpose?
Yeah, right.
And that's the three layers that we now have to think about.
And that purpose gives you access to do what things.
And that's those are the layers of complexity.
And if you if you think of it from that perspective,
that's how the layer of the complexity of identity systems have that,
that agents force, for us to be able to solve a lot of these safety
concerns across system.
Yeah.
Okay.
Cool, I love the session analogy because it's something you can kind of relate to.
And sessions are interesting.
Sessions are things that they might get invalidated and require a new.
A bunch of triggers.
Most common time,
you know, that's been idle for a while, or maybe just sitting there.
Sometimes it's an action that has been performed
that kind of requires a, a variety of those.
So maybe let's sort of go into indeed a little bit of the solution.
Absolutely.
So what are
what are the types of sort of tools or new capabilities that are out there?
I know Keycard is kind of one of those on it,
but give us a little
bit of the families of ways to tackle this sort of new challenge.
Yeah.
I think there's there are many different
sort of solutions on market that kind of message to, to this type of thing.
But I think like the step back and think about
what are the new technologies or protocols that are emerging to start solving this.
And then we can kind of discuss about different ways.
So I think there's really, if I'm sitting in the chair
as a security person, I'm thinking about two things.
One, I'm thinking about how do I find my shadow agents or my shadow AI.
It's always a conversation.
Security is what are the things that are happening that I don't know about, right.
So I can quantify. You're obsessed with shadows.
Shadows. It's like, yeah, can I see a shadow?
Is a user doing something I didn't intend or was a system misconfigured
or whatever? Right. This is this is governance.
And there's a lot of money
made in governance and security, which is quantifying effectively risk.
And then there's the golden path, right.
And in all security solutions, in all dynamics, you always have.
Hey, here is how we're going to find all the risk.
Well, once we've identified risk, because a lot of the risk
is not people doing the wrong thing, they don't have the wrong intention.
They just don't know how to do the right thing.
That is like the secure pathway.
And then you have your solutions that are, what are the secure pathway.
Exactly.
And so you always in most markets and in most problem spaces
you have, let's go find and quantify all the risk.
And then you have, okay, here's the place we, we go, and, you know, over time
as markets consolidate they often tend to be the same thing but.
Moved on from the shadow to the road. Exactly.
But and the road is typically the infrastructure part.
Right.
And we saw that with the rise of social on the web,
with the rise of OAuth, do things like Auth0 come along?
Made it really easy for developers to build social login on their website
and user management, which turned out to be a really hard problem.
And so a lot of people, that's why that market exists.
And then
of course, we had for internal workflow, we had, like, things like Okta that rose
and it made real easy,
have a golden pathway for me to log into stuff.
And then you, of course,
had all your governance functionality that came as well. Right?
These are all kind of examples of places where you would sort of centrally define.
Exactly or sort of identity Europe in the case of the system, but
then you'd be able to kind of plug that in places.
And even with the rise of cloud, we had things like HashiCorp Vault
in Terraform that allowed me to configure
IAM systems, or provide a place for me to store long lived secrets. And so much.
The last era was about, where do I, where's the golden path? Right now
with the change, with the rise of agents, agents
basically break a lot of assumptions of how all those things work together,
because they kind of work across different systems.
They can work on behalf of your customers.
They can work on behalf of yourself. They can work on.
They can just be pieces of code that are running in your stack,
maintaining your software factory, deploying, debugging things.
You have all these different interactions that are no longer human driven,
but they do exist. And how do you manage that?
But the fundamental issue is what are the new technologies
or techniques that are coming out to help do the session mission attestation.
And so in OAuth
you have some movement there that's trying to, trying to take over OAuth.
Some of the stuff that Okta came up with is called Cross App Access.
It solves some of the problems with it, but it doesn't solve all things.
So that's ID-JAG for those that are watching.
And then on there's a.
Net new protocol called Agent Auth, written by Dick Hardt,
who has a net new approach on a protocol to try and solve these,
these mission session orientation, and move away from long lived secrets.
So those are some of the protocols that are emerging.
And then the different approaches today are, you're going to, is how do I find
and quantify
what risk I have, whether it's on my endpoint
and my production stack or my cloud accounts.
And then you sort of have your golden path things
of how do I actually enable my developers or my customers or my employees
to be able to find, build and use agents successfully in sort of the golden path?
Yeah. Okay.
So let me kind of echo back some, a little bit of that.
So like the old so you have the sort of broader challenges.
One of the projects around OAuth, it's about sort of allowing agents
identifying as agents, not masquerading as humans, to use today.
I guess we would have all seen hey,
ran the login and sort of opened up your browser.
You're making a film on it.
This is you authenticating as a human, then giving that key now to the agent instead.
Can we sort of create a protocol that allow the agent, allows the agents
to sort of authenticate as an agent and sort of have the appropriate. Yes.
Okay. So that makes sense.
And that's like a bit more of a sort of like a technical path
with some of the price identity, but it doesn't solve the sort of the, the,
the mission. Exactly problem.
Exactly.
Before, I guess the sort of the second bucket
is more around that sort of mission identity. Exactly.
And for the mission identity, like, where is the point in time in which
and who is involved in saying, fine, there's a mission, you've done it.
But like, what are the permissions that are allowed over here?
It seems untenable that that would be a human
that will come along every time and say, okay, fine.
I figure it out that what you're trying to do is compose an email.
You'll have these permissions versus, you know, you're optimizing a database.
So maybe you are allowed to modify an index. Exactly.
I think there's there's two parts to to this.
One is everybody individuals and companies,
more companies and individuals are going to have things that just say,
you know, no agent can do this without me being involved, right?
For me personally, it's probably spending over a certain amount of money
or deleting data, right?
Those are like if you're deleting I want to I want to make that decision.
Right. Because I care.
Or if you're sending an email, I actually do care deeply or.
Those are reasonable.
Those are not mission decisions though.
Like just ground rules.
Yeah, they're just ground rules.
Now when it comes to mission decisions, this is really where patterns like LLM
as a judge start to, start to emerge because you're, you're using,
you know, a reasoning engine to reason about whether something is reasonable.
And then ostensibly you basically based on this,
does the system think this is reasonable? Okay.
If it's not reasonable, now who decides what we do as a result? Is that
no, absolutely not, because it's hit some deterministic guardrail.
We say no, we'd never let delete.
Oh, it's trying to do X, right.
Should this go to the security team?
The security team
then has like a system that reviews it or should actually go back to the person
that's operating on behalf of and says, hey, this agent tried to do this thing.
Yeah.
Is this aligned with your what you were trying to get done right?
And the biggest challenge we have today when it comes to agent
security is how do we actually not end up with consent fatigue, right.
Like, the worst part about the yes, no, allow always dialog
is you just click yes because I'm not going to read it.
Right.
And that's always been one of the biggest challenges
in security is how do I have a security system
that only sounds the alarm when appropriate, relevant?
Exactly. Otherwise you lose all the signals.
So the mission componentry, one part of it is getting all the protocols
and the functionality in place so that you can sort of federate out.
What is it that this person said this thing's supposed to be doing?
And then the second component
is the system around that that can actually make judgment calls.
And the better the system around it is that making judgment calls,
the more, like, the less interrupts the users will have, right?
And a lower risk profile decision we made.
And that's more trust and a pathway to higher autonomy.
Yeah, yeah. Makes sense. Okay.
So you have to do that.
So, again, agents all the way down, something into it.
So you need the infrastructure.
We have these two open protocols that I guess are forming, right.
Like standards. Take a moment. Yes.
And, and then you have, I guess, kind of two new concepts,
which is you have these missions, you have to give them an identity
which is already like a little bit hard to sort of.
Wrap your head around. Yeah.
But then also you need to figure out what is the authorization,
what are the permissions, which will be a subset of the overall agent identity.
Exactly. So what are the.
Let's sort of get down then to the tools themselves that are available.
Right.
If I am
building agents and I'm sold, you know, like this is a problem.
This is a concern. Yes, I have this.
What are the tools available to me?
Yeah.
You know, today
there's this big battle in the ecosystem that I'm sure Guy has talked to
about with somebody.
There's this battle between CLI versus MCP, right?
And so we kind of have, you know, you have CLI tools
which very much have not, don't have any really auth system built into them.
And then you have MCP,
which, the nice thing about MCP is it comes out of the box with, like, OAuth support.
So in order to be an MCP you have to have OAuth support.
And that OAuth support gives a pathway for saying
is does this thing actually support some of the concepts that I talked about.
Right.
And there's there's two broad ecosystems where there are solutions
that only work for MCP.
And then there's some solutions that only work for CLIs.
And the question really is is that sufficient?
Because what we know is there's a set of agents, computers,
agents, specifically coding agents, that CLI tools are their bread and butter.
Right. They're just really good at it.
And that makes them fast.
And it's one of the reasons that, like, Opus and GPT-5
really were the breakthrough models on these computer
use things and led us to new level of autonomy.
And then you have sort of MCP only.
And the question is to think about what is the agent,
what type of tools is the agent need to have access to,
and what type of agent should have running in my ecosystem to do that?
And how do I integrate that if if it's an agent that is operating inside
my company, I probably want that to integrate with my IDP
and I want but I want to think of the IDP slightly
differently for agents and for users, because they're actually slightly
different problem statements, broadly speaking.
And then the tools on the market tend to be like an IDP solution.
There's some tools in the market that look like an MCP gateway,
which is a common topic, very much designed for MCP.
It's a giant proxy.
And there's other things that are designed
specifically for solving this sort of agent
agent communication in a federated manner.
And those are the two like landscape solutions at the moment.
And then, of course, you have your traditional last generation
sort of vendors like your Privileged Access Management.
That was very, very hot topic.
So how do I give a human access to like a Postgres running in my Amazon or my GCP?
Very big important problem.
Things like a CyberArk, that was bought by Palo Alto, was a good example of that.
And those are sort of the buckets.
And then of course you have your I'm building an agent that someone uses.
And how does my agent or my MCP or whatever
allow users to authenticate so it can carry down identity and access.
And those are the broad buckets of problems.
So like
everything that you described right now is very like enterprise solutions for it.
So in the organization you figure out
how do I represent agent identities in my IDP? Yes.
How do I sort of systematically control access to my systems by routing.
Kind of, or blessing, some sort of access granter.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
Having it be accessed via CLI or SDK and run along.
So those are very like enterprise wide.
Are the solutions all, like, some of the problems that you've described
are things that I might as an individual or as a team also say, well,
within, within my sort of processes that I'm running here,
I want some sort of mission identity, mission permissions, definitions on it.
Are there solutions that also work within, within that resolution?
I mean, certainly that's something we're trying to do with
Keycard, is trying to empower teams to be able to just quickly and easily
pick up agents, but also quickly and easily build their own agents
where they're not constrained, whether it's MCP or CLI or a specific scale.
We're trying to build it across.
And so we sort of look at it's it's actually not
MCP or CLI, it's both, but it's also not PAM.
It's all three combined.
And how
you bring these different identities
and these different postures into one system
that's really easy to adopt and build with is how we think about the problem.
And that's where we're coming from.
And, you know, I think the challenge.
Tell us a little bit more about that, which is how would you.
So if you were to use Keycard. Yeah.
What does that entail.
You know, if I'm and if you well I guess you sort of choose
whether that sort of like if I'm a, you know, the big boss kind of
kind of system or if I'm a developer. Developer.
Yeah.
But what does it sort of feel like, you know, like, what am I doing?
Yeah, absolutely.
So, the way we've architected our solution is
if I'm, you know, using Claude Code, I want to give access to some things.
I download the Keycard CLI, I can now run Claude or Cursor
or Pi or insert your, your harness of choice, with Keycard.
We integrate with the hook system.
We then, you basically tell Keycard, hey, this agent can access these things
and it could be a set of MCPs,
or it could be a set of CLI tools or tool calls on my behalf.
And then we make, from that point on, no longer do you actually have to. Yes.
No, allow always consent dialog. Keycard makes those determinations for you.
And then you get to say you know what?
If it's a delete, I should probably review.
And that thing, whether that thing
is running on my local device or if it's running in a sandbox
someplace or it's cloud, it works the same way across all.
So one insertion point to allow your to allow your agent to evolve
into a software factory and have autonomy.
And then if you're on the flip side, I'm
trying to build a service, I'm trying to build an agent or a tool
that agents can talk to
with the latest, greatest protocols without having to be an auth expert.
You can use our SDKs, which then allow you to build those types of things
that your agents can.
With this.
Well, and so in that context, you are providing a means of some sort
of central definition of logic, I guess, or sort of like the decision making.
Yeah. And then you are connecting that.
Exactly like the two, the two value propositions are one.
Hey, here's like a smart engine that can make good decisions
about who should approve what, and is able to take your input.
The second is, hey, I kind of handle the proliferation of agents.
You have many, many agents.
You have the same kind of logic applied at various places.
Exactly.
And from there, connect that up to like some
the parent system of, you know, how does a, how does sort of a central platform team
convey down some of those decisions into different desktops?
Exactly.
So, how does, we really are focused on how do we enable that individual developer
to find lots of success, then how we let them graduate from that
to a team of people going together across, independent of the harness.
Right? Yeah. Access.
What resources and what circumstance.
And over time, how does that give sort of that
centralized security team, the platform team, both the enablement
function of how do I roll this out across the entire organization,
but also has a security team get the confidence to say, you know what,
we can say yes to this high, high degree of autonomy
because we feel like we have the security in place that we require to do it.
Yeah. Hey everyone!
Hope you're enjoying the episode so far.
Our team is working really hard behind the scenes to bring you the best guests,
so we can have the most informative conversations about agentic development,
whether that's talking about the latest
tools, the most efficient workflows, or defining best practices.
But for whatever reason, many of you have yet to subscribe to the channel.
If you're enjoying the podcast and want us to continue to bring you
the very best content,
please do us a favor and hit that subscribe button.
It really does make a difference and lets us continue to improve
the quality of our guests and build an even better product for you.
All right, back to the episode.
Yeah. And so, cool.
So I love that. And I love the sort of the dev
taste of sort of, sort of the Keycard stuff on it.
And it is,
you know,
like I'm a believer in the bottom up, although with the it's not necessarily
bottom up, but that sort of developer experience clearly.
Also the world has a lot of sort of a passion for,
for central control systems to come along.
And I guess that's the tension that sort of plays out.
Neither is like right or wrong.
It's just about what is the emphasis at a different time?
How much do you indeed kind of define the guardrails in a broad, broad sense.
But I think a key, a key takeaway,
you know, the many, many, many kind of interesting things
and kind of all this description and things for outlining that.
But this notion of these mission identities
and agentically decided permission set for that.
From there, the ability to define those, enforce them properly,
observe them, improve them over time, reason around them, and enforce them.
All of those are probably evolutions of the system.
Over time, that core new mission identity and permissions are sort of a new entity.
Exactly.
That's the final thing that we're focused on at Key
card is, how do you understand what agents are doing?
Yeah.
How do you allow agents to do things without having to artificially define
all the strict, long lived policy?
And that's what we do.
You get there by being able to describe high level, like, you know what,
these are the situations where I'm really not okay with an agent doing something.
For me, it's a lot about deletion.
And in all other circumstances, I'm okay with a system
making the judgment call on my behalf.
But whether it's allowed.
And that's how we can have this sort of high degree of how we can move towards
high degree, higher degree of autonomy without bad downstream things happening.
And one of the biggest challenges with that, talking to a lot of,
in the enterprise, we're using individual devs, is this is great.
Like conceptually it's great, but how do I roll this out?
And that's where like high level
policy combined with, like, the LLM as a judge feature helps people see.
Oh, okay. So I'm not sitting there. Yeah.
Artificially defining hundreds and hundreds
and hundreds of lines of policy files, which was what we learned.
I think there are a lot of security tools.
And last generation is that that's where deployment went wrong and failed.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah.
Because it's not like when it came to humans, we were good.
Exactly.
Like. No, we were bad. Yeah.
It's like a bad problem. Yeah.
And I think the reality of of, of kind of many,
many aspects of technology is the problems that were a nuisance.
But we can kind of kind of get by with in the pre agent era.
But they were not great. The best teams handled them.
You know, those are now intolerable. Exactly.
The agent.
I often I often say to people that the best practices of cloud
are now base requirements for, for agents.
And we certainly seen those sandboxes and cloud environments and everything
and still true about.
All we're good before, but, and the same was true for like waterfall to, to cloud.
That's true as well.
Yeah. Yes.
So I guess
kind of before we close off here, I'll ask one foolish thing, which is the future.
I love it.
I love to predict the future. I do this all the time. Yeah.
So I mean, one aspect of it is with all this identity and evolutions of it,
you know, what is the transition period to it
and what is immediately caring and all that.
But if we if we leapfrog all of that and we say like three years from now,
yeah, feels like a lifetime. Away.
What do you think will be the sort of the state
of, of the ecosystem when it comes to how do we define these identities.
Yeah, I think I think there's a couple of things.
One is, first and foremost, new protocols will actually have been deployed.
Right.
And so right now we're really sitting on last generations
like OAuth-like implementations.
And it turns out most of them are not very good.
And we're seeing a lot of that when, you know, you go using MCP
from some of your favorite providers, you're like, well, why does this not work
the way that I actually thought it would work?
Why does this require all this?
I think, I think the future of the internet and such, agents will make everything
feel pluggable, and interoperability will be incredibly important.
And you'll see lots of companies really want
because they want to have an agent forward experience.
They'll really make interoperability across agent clients a high priority,
which means that, like most people
will be focused on actually building up net new auth components to support this.
And that will then, from an end user perspective, make actually pulling
a bunch of tools together so much easier and so much better.
I think that on the flip side, what we'll see is specifically in the
enterprise, we're going to see people move where there used to be a lot of silos,
and those silos are driven by how hard it was to write policy to less silos
and higher degrees of productivity and higher degrees of context sharing,
both because there's huge promise, but also because the identity and access
systems will upgrade to the point where allows that interoperability
and the enterprise will allow these things to communicate to each other,
while the security team will have the things that they need to say
to keep the company secure, which is often been part of the reason
that those systems didn't connect, because they didn't
have a good way to actually manage information sharing.
Yeah. That's like a very optimistic view of the future.
I know the protocols will be like it's not a given that standards
will be defined in three years on it, and the sort of the system will do it.
So that is definitely the sort of the aspiration
which is these systems will, will, and I guess I guess kind of the, the, the,
the driver is the belief that just like agents are making sufficiently
forcing function, that we have no option but to. Exactly.
And that's certainly been the history of identity and access for the last
30 years is like, it's not the consumer that is really forced the evolution.
It's excluding online shopping with TLS, it really has been the enterprise
that has driven the requirement because what they want
is a productivity gains, or they have the security requirements
and they go out and say to all their vendors, yeah, you really need
you have to implement this, like for me to keep spending my $25 million with you.
And of course, the vendors say, well, we're not turning that money away.
We really need that revenue. So we're going to go implement it.
And also because all over enterprise folks are asking for it.
And I think what's unique about this era of of agents
specifically is we're seeing agents at work
be adopted much faster, with much higher degrees of ROI than agents at home.
And, you know, that's an inversion of some things
we've seen previously, but it's certainly true now.
And so I think as a result of that,
that will force like the the security stack, the next generation
security stack to evolve much faster than I would have typically suggested.
Yeah. I think that's a good look.
I think I relate to that.
Maybe it's like a little bit optimistic on it, but I think nothing is better.
Like, it's a strong forcing function,
that it is definitely well fueled from a VC.
The main of it in terms of funding the transition,
probably because of this sort of urgency. Exactly.
Yeah, yeah.
Thanks a lot for coming in and demystifying,
kind of helping us understand identity on it.
Looking forward to seeing,
you know, Keycard, and in general kind of just rolled out, mature for it.
Absolutely. So thanks a lot for coming in. Thanks for having me.
And if you're interested in Keycard, you can find us at keycard.ai.
And we'd happy to show you a demo and help
you see how you can adopt coding agents and build your own agents at scale.
Very cool.
And thanks everybody for tuning in and I hope you join us for the next one.
The AI Native Dev is brought to you
by Tessl, the package manager for skills and context.
Your hosts are Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple.
Our producer is Tom Dowler.
The AI Native Dev is not just a podcast, it's a community.
And we host monthly meetups at the Tessl offices in central London.
Visit tessl.io/community to learn more and I hope to see you there.